A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine Administration Electronic Files, Email, 2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)
Library of Virginia
- Series IX. Secretary of Health and Human Resources Electronic Files, 2004-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)., Extent: 51288 emails.
  - Series IX. Secretary of Health and Human Resources Electronic Files, Subseries A. Marilyn Tavenner Email, 2006-2010.
    Notable email includes: email from Ray Ratke, Chief Deputy Commissioner DMHMRSAS, dated 17 April 2007, to Secretary of HHR, Marilyn Tavenner on Seung-Hui Cho's contacts with New River Valley CSB; email from Stephen Harms, Deputy Secretary of HHR, dated 11 May 2007, to Marilyn Tavenner, forwarding an email between Leslie Anderson, Office of Licensing, DMHMRSAS, and Ray Ratke, dated 11 May 2007 documenting Cho's contacts with St. Albans; email from Stephen Harms, Deputy Secretary of HHR, dated 11 May 2007, to Marilyn Tavenner, regarding licensing reviews of New River Valley CSB and St. Albans (Cho); email from Gail Jaspen, Deputy Secretary of HHR, dated 11 May 2007, to Marilyn Tavenner and Robert Stroube, forwarding the Virginia Department of Health's After Action Report addressing the 16 April 2007 Virginia Tech Multiple Casualty Incident; email from Bill Leighty, dated 15 May 2007, to Stephen Harms, regarding DMHMRSAS Virginia Tech after action report; email from Gail Jaspen, Deputy Secretary of HHR, dated 12 September 2007, to Marilyn Tavenner, Larry Roberts and Brian Shepard, forwarding three reports in response to the Virginia Tech Review Panel report from the Office of the Chief Medical Examiner, Department of Health and Department of Emergency Management Services; email from Stephen Harms, Deputy Secretary of HHR, dated 28 April 2006, to Marilyn Tavenner, on administration metrics-included in this thread is an email from Governor Kaine, dated 27 April 2006, to Pierce Homer, Marilyn Tavenner, Preston Bryant and Tom Morris, listing measures of success for four main issues; email from Marilyn Tavenner, dated 17 November 2009, to Wayne Turnage, Stephen Harms and Brian Shepard, forwarding the HHR hand-off list for the McDonnell Administration; email from Wayne Turnage, dated 16 January 2008, to Tom Morris, Marilyn Tavenner, Anthony Conyers, and Bill Cannaday, describing the objective of an upcoming meeting for a new office to direct Governor Kaine's Pre-K initiative; email from Wayne Turnage, dated 25 January 2008, to Brian Shepard, Suzette Denslow, Jennie Moline, and Stephen Harms (Marilyn Tavenner cc'd), describing proposed structure of Office of Early Childhood Education; email from Nikki Nicholau, dated 17 April 2007, to Marilyn Tavenner, transmitting a draft of the Virginia Dept. of Social Service's Talking Points for Virginia Tech; email from Stephen Harms, dated 1 May 2007, to Marilyn Tavenner, re: Inspector General's review of Cho's records; email from Marilyn Tavenner, dated 5 January 2007, to Brian Shepard and Delacey Skinner, sharing Tavenner's thoughts on Governor Kaine's upcoming State of the Commonwealth address; email from Tim Kaine, dated 29 April 2007, to Brian Shepard (Marilyn Tavenner, et al copied), containing a draft of a draft Executive Directive 7 (07) - Reporting Critical Safety Data to the Central Criminal Records Exchange - written by Shepard and edited by Kaine (See EO 50); email from Tim Kaine, dated 4 January 2007, to Brian Shepard, Delacey Skinner and Marilyn Tavenner, containing Kaine's edits and thoughts on his upcoming State of the Commonwealth address; email from Stephen Harms, dated 20 April 2007, to Bill Leighty and Larry Roberts (Tavenner copied), transmitting Virginia's Civil Commitment Process; email from Stephen Harms, dated 26 April 2007, to James Reinhard (Tavenner copied), forwarding draft of Executive Directive 7 (07) Central Criminal Records Exchange(See EO 50) (see additional emails on this topic dated 28-29 April 2007); and email from Brian Shepard, dated 23 April 2007, to Marilyn Tavenner and John Marshall, transmitting copy of a memorandum to Governor Kaine on mental health treatment and firearms ownership (see also email from Stephen Harms, dated 23 April 2007, to Brian Shepard with draft of memorandum).
    Correspondents include: Karen Angelic, Joseph Bowman, Gena Boyle, Preston Bryant, Debbie Burcham, Kristin Burhop, Jim Burns, Alicia Cavanaugh, Jeff Corbin, Scott Crawford, Alicia Cavanaugh, Aneesh Chopra, Julie Christopher, Matthew Cobb, Anthony Conyers, Scott Crawford, Robert Crouch, Suzette Denslow, Heidi Dix, Emily Ehrlichman, Eileen Filler-Corn, Patrick Finnerty, Steve Ford, Thomas Gates, Kathy Glazer, Doug Gray, Matt Gross, David Hallock, Phil Hamilton, Joyce Hann, Stephen Harms, Jane Hickey, Joe Hilbert, Anne Holton, Karen Jackson, Gail Jaspen, Cindi Jones, Tim Kaine, Lisa Kaplowitz, Aryana Khalid, Bob Kocher, Heidi Lawyer, Bill Leighty, Alfonso Lopez, Bob Marshall, Melissa Mayes, Kim McGaughey, Jennie Moline, Bill Murray, Linda Nablo, Laurie Naismith, Martha Pulley, Ray Ratke, James Reinhard, Sheldon Retchin, Karen Remley, Gail Robinson, Katie Roeper, James Rothrock, Sandra Ryals, Charles Savage, Margaret Schultze, Brian Shepard, Michael Shook, Delacey Skinner, Julie Stanley, Lem Stewart, Robert Stroube, Dan Timberlake, Wayne Turnage, Shannon Valentine, Jody Wagner, Ruth Anne Walker, Joy Yeh, and Nick Young.
  - Series IX. Secretary of Health and Human Resources Electronic Files, Subseries B. Gail Jaspen Email, 2006-2008.
    This subseries contains 23554 emails in one PST file: KaineLibgjaspen.pst. Gail Jaspen served as Deputy Secretary of Health and Human Resources from January 2006 to August 2008. Jaspen left the Kaine administration in August 2008 when she accepted a position as Chief Deputy Director of the Virginia Department of Forensic Sciences. Prior to joining the Kaine administration, Jaspen worked under Governor Mark R. Warner (2002-2006) as Chief Deputy Director of the Department of Health Professions, and as Deputy Counselor to the Governor and Special Policy Assistant for Public Safety.
    The KaineLibgjaspen.pst contains 23554 email messages sent and received by Gail Jaspen between January 2006 and August 2008. There are 184 privacy protected and confidential emails in this PST file that are restricted for 75 years per Code of Virginia 2.2-3800, 32.1-127.1:03, 42.1-78, 54.1-2523, 63.2-102, and 63.2-103. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: personal information, health records, social services information, child support enforcement, and attorney-client communications.
    Subjects include: state agency correspondence, issues, and weekly reports from HHR agencies (Virginia Department for the Aging, Virginia Department of Medical Assistance, Virginia Department of Health Professionals, Office of the Inspector General, Virginia Board for People with Disabilities, Virginia Department of Social Services, Assistive Technology Loan Fund Authority/NewWell Fund, DMHMRSAS, Virginia Department for the Blind and Vision Impaired, Virginia Department for the Deaf and Hard of Hearing, Virginia Department of Rehabilitative Services, Virginia Department of Health, Community Integration for People with Disabilities, Office of Comprehensive Services (OCS), Virginia Tobacco Settlement Foundation, and Virginia Department of Social Services); state budget issues including agency budget reductions; legislative files (agency positions on pending legislation; administration's positions on bills; enrolled bill reviews; legislative action updates; and legislative contacts); VITA/NG issues; No Wrong Door initiative/Senior Navigator; Medicaid; Family Access to Medical Insurance Security (FAMIS); adoption/foster care; TANF (Temporary Assistance for Needy Families); smoking ban for restaurants; COPN (Certificate of Public Need); Mirant plant in Alexandria; influenza pandemic planning; Hurricane Ernest situation reports; Governor's Working Group on Early Childhood Initiatives; Health Reform Commission; Jaspen's notes from cabinet and deputies' meetings; Virginia Tech shooting (immediate aftermath and legislative recommendations from VT Review Panel); Assisted Living Facilities Administrator Regulations; and State Workforce Sub Cabinet.
    Notable email includes: email from Robert Stroube, dated 11 May 2007, to Marilyn Tavenner and Gail Jaspen, forwarding the Virginia Department of Health After Action Report for the 16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech; email from Gail Jaspen, Deputy Secretary of HHR, dated 11 May 2007, to Marilyn Tavenner and Robert Stroube, forwarding the Virginia Department of Health's After Action Report addressing the 16 April 2007 Virginia Tech Multiple Casualty Incident; email thread between Gail Jaspen and Marilyn Tavenner, dated 13 November 2007, transmitting SHHR Talking Points on the response to Virginia Tech tragedy for the Senate Finance retreat; email from Gail Jaspen, dated 24 April 2006, to Wayne Turnage, with attachment containing her edits to Healthcare Reform White Paper; email from Heidi Dix, dated 8 October 2007, to Gail Jaspen and Marilyn Tavenner, containing draft legislation banning smoking in restaurants; email from Wayne Turnage, dated 18 January 2008, to Workforce Sub Cabinet members, on the importance of delivering to the Governor a MOU agreement for comprehensive 1-Stops; and email from Danny LeBlanc, dated 17 March 2008, transmitting signed State MOU concerning One Stop Centers.
    Correspondents include: Marilyn Batan, Mark Bowles, Joseph Bowman, Gena Boyle, Curtis Brown, Preston Bryant, Debbie Burcham, Kristin Burhop, Alicia Cavanaugh, Aneesh Chopra, Julie Christopher, Anthony Conyers, Jeff Corbin, Christy Crowther, Jay DeBoer, Heidi Dix, Suzette Denslow, Chris Durrer, Michael Evans, Marcella Fierro, Eileen Filler-Corn, Patrick Finnerty, Kathy Glazer, Suzanne Gore, Steven Gravely, Lynette Hammond, Joyce Hann, Stephen Harms, Sherrie Harrington, Bo Harris, Hubert Harris, Joe Hilbert, Scott Hippert, Asha Holloman, Anne Holton, Ray Hopkins, Catherina Hutchins, Cindi Jones, Tim Kaine, Lisa Kaplowitz, Martin Kent, Aryana Khalid, Marty Kilgore, Jeffrey Lake, Robert Lanier, Heidi Lawyer, Bill Leighty, Alfonso Lopez, Richard Martin, Robert Mauskapf, Kim McGaughey, Martha Mead, Mark Monson, Bill Murray, Linda Nablo, Robert Nebiker, Nikki Nicholau, Pat Pettie, Leslie Prince, Martha Pulley, James Reinhard, Gail Robinson, Katie Roeper, James Rothrock, John Russell, Sandra Ryals, Margaret Schultze, Brian Shepard, Julie Stanley, James Stewart, Robert Stroube, Marilyn Tavenner, Wayne Turnage, Aaron Ver, Joey Wallace, Emily Wingfield, Elaine Yeatts, Nick Young, Neil Zahradka, David Ziegler, Mary Zoller, and Richard Zorn.
  - Series IX. Secretary of Health and Human Resources Electronic Files, Subseries C. Heidi Dix Email, 2006-2009.
    This subseries contains 2412 emails in three PST files: 2006LibHDix.pst, 2007LibHDix.pst, and KaineLibHDix.pst. Heidi Dix served as Assistant Secretary of Health and Human Resources from 17 April 2006 to July 2007 and Assistant Deputy Secretary of Health and Human Resources from July 2007 to January 2009. Dix left the Kaine Administration in January 2009 when she accepted a position as Deputy Commissioner of the Department of Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services (DMHMRSAS).
    - 2006LibHDix.pst, 2006-2007.
      The 2006LibHDix.pst contains 171 emails sent and received by Heidi Dix from 2006 to 2007. Three privacy protected and confidential emails in this PST file are restricted for 75 years per Code of Virginia 2.2-3800 and 42.1-78. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: records containing personal information.
      Subjects include: HB 110 (2006) and proposed revisions-agency reports on aging population; Governor's Health Reform Commission (Access Work group, LTC Work group); Congressional briefing documents; and legislation.
      Correspondents include: Gail Jaspen, Heidi Lawyer, Bill Lukhard, William Peterson, and Marilyn Tavenner.
    - 2007LibHDix.pst, 2006-2007.
      The 2007LibHDix.pst contains 544 emails sent and received by Heidi Dix from 2006 to 2007. There are two privacy protected and confidential emails in this PST file that are restricted for 75 years per Code of Virginia 2.2-3800 and 42.1-78. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: records containing personal information.
      Subjects include: legislation (primarily legislative action summaries and legislative contacts for Department of Social Services 2007 related legislation); budget requests; and Governor's Health Reform Commission (Access Work group and LTC Work group) including draft reports, presentations and meeting agendas and minutes.
      Correspondents include: Henry Claypool, Michael Cook, Brian Coyne, Steve Ford, Gail Jaspen, Cindi Jones, Jean Kane, Heidi Lawyer, Beth Ludden, William Lukhard, Richard Martin, William Peterson, Sheldon Retchin, Lisa Sprinkel, Marilyn Tavenner, and Wayne Turnage.
    - KaineLibHDix.pst, 2007-2009.
      The KaineLibHDix.pst contains 1697 emails sent and received by Heidi Dix from January 2007 and January 2009. There are 129 privacy protected and confidential emails in this PST file that are restricted for 75 years per Code of Virginia 2.2-3800, 32.1-127.1:03, and 42.1-78. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: records containing personal information, medical information and attorney-client communications.
      Subjects include: agency correspondence (Dept. of Medical Assistance Services, DMHMRSAS, Department of Social Services, Office of the Comprehensive Services Act, and Department of Health); Medicaid/Medicare; Virginia Office for Protection and Advocacy (VOPA) case; budget, budget cuts; legislation, changing name of Department of Mental Health, Mental Retardation, and Substance Abuse Services (DMHMRSAS) to Department of Behavioral Health and Developmental Services (BHDS) in October 2008; reports to the General Assembly; Legislative contacts; child support enforcement; relocation of Department of Social Services offices in Richmond metro area; foster care; Senior Navigator; Comprehensive Services Act (CSA); Autism Spectrum Disorders and Developmental Disabilities work group; Virginia Commission on Immigration; and housing task force.
      Correspondents include: Kristin Burhop, Alicia Cavanaugh, Victoria Cochran, Anthony Conyers, Emily Ehrlichmann, Patrick Finnerty, Steve Ford, Matt Gross, David Hallock, Bo Harris, Joe Hilbert, Gail Jaspen, Cindi Jones, Tim Kaine, Aryana Khalid, Heidi Lawyer, Marianne McGhee, Kim McGaughey, Ray Ratke, James Reinhard, Jim Rothrock, Margaret Schultze, Richard Silwoski, Julia Stanley, Marilyn Tavenner, Wayne Turnage, Ruth Anne Walker, and Nick Young.
  - Series IX. Secretary of Health and Human Resources Electronic Files, Subseries D. Aryana Khalid Email, 2006-2009.
    This subseries contains 9696 emails in two PST files: KaineLibakhalid.pst and AKHALID.PST. Aryana C. Khalid served as Assistant Secretary of Health and Human Resources from October 2006 to July 2007 and Assistant Deputy Secretary of Health and Human Resources from July 2007 to 3 April 2009. Khalid left the Kaine administration in April 2009 when she accepted a position in the Office of Senator Mark R. Warner (D-VA). Prior to joining the Kaine administration, Khalid worked for Hospital Corporation of America (HCA) in the Chief Operating Officer Development Program.
    - KaineLibakhalid.pst, 2006-2009.
      The KaineLibakhalid.pst contains 9685 emails sent and received by Aryana Khalid between October 2006 and January 2009. There are 63 privacy protected and confidential emails in this PST file that are restricted for 75 years per Code of Virginia 2.2-3800, 32.1-127.1:03, and 42.1-78. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: records containing personal information, medical information and attorney-client communications.
      Subjects include: agency correspondence and issues (Dept. of Medical Assistance Services, DMHMRSAS, Department of Social Services, Office of the Comprehensive Services Act, and Department of Health); Medicaid; reauthorization of SCHIP (State Children's Health Insurance Program) (in Virginia it's called Family Access to Medical Insurance Security (FAMIS)); HHR legislation; preferred drug list (PDL); Seven Hills Nursing Facility in the City of Richmond, noncompliance with Center for Medicare and Medicaid Services (CMS) requirements; rate increase for Medicaid ambulance providers; over payment of Medicaid fees to ambulance providers; No Wrong Door; Senior Navigator; Windsor Nursing Home; RJ Reynolds/Patrick County Memorial Hospital; smoking ban in state office buildings and restaurants; abstinence/abortion; Methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA) virus; legislative contacts with the Virginia Department of Health (VDH); media alerts from VDH; Federal appropriations requests for Virginia including Federal Medical Assistance Percentage (FMAP); workforce development (One Stop); health insurance; talking points; Legislative files for 2007, 2008 and 2009 General Assembly session for HHR related bills (Legislative Action Update, Legislative Action Summary, Enrolled Bill Review, Decision Brief, legislative contacts, notes from committee meetings, talking points); state budget development/cuts for 2008 and 2009; American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (ARRA) projects (federal stimulus package); NGA Childhood Obesity Prevention Grant; Weekly Reports from SHHR agencies (includes VDH Flu Updates to Governor Kaine), 2007-2009; and Health Benefits Task Force; Health IT; Health Reform Commission.
      Correspondents include: Carl Armstrong, Bennett Blodgett, Gena Boyle, Barbara Brown, Kristin Burhop, James Burns, Alicia Cavanaugh, Aneesh Chopra, Scott Crawford, Robert Crouch, Brian Davis, Heidi Dix, Patrick Finnerty, Joe Flores, Steve Ford, Thomas Gates, Kathy Glazer, Lisa Hague, David Hallock, Stephen Harms, Maurice Henderson II, JoAnne Kirk Henry, Joe Hilbert, Gary Janak, Gail Jaspen, Cindi Jones, Tim Kaine, Bob Kocher (McKinsey); Heidi Lawyer, Alfonso Lopez, Richard Martin, Michael Mathews, Kim McGaughey, Michael McMahon, Martha Mead, Susan Motley, Bill Murray, Linda Nablo, Karen Remley, Gail Robinson, James Rothrock, Megan Root, Sandra Ryals, Margaret Schultz, Brian Shepard, Shawna Shields, Delacey Skinner, Julie Stanley, Robert Stroube, Craig Tanio, Marilyn Tavenner, Jeff Tiller, Wayne Turnage, Ruth Anne Walker, Kathy Wibberly, and Elaine Yeatts.
    - AKHALID.PST, 2009.
      The AKHALID.PST contains 11 emails sent and received by Aryana Khalid between 19 March 2009 and 3 April 2009.
      Subjects include: Regional Strike Force meeting and Health IT.
  - Series IX. Secretary of Health and Human Resources Electronic Files, Subseries E. Julie A. Stanley Email, 2005-2010.
    This subseries contains 669 emails in one PST file: KaineLibjstanley.pst. Julie A. Stanley served as the Director of the Office of Community Integration for People with Disabilities from 2004 to 2010. Governor Mark Warner created the Office of Community Integration for People with Disabilities in 2004 by executive order (EO 61). Warner's executive order was part of the Commonwealth's response to the U.S. Supreme Court's Olmstead v. L.C. decision, the Americans with Disability Act, and the Virginians with Disabilities Act to provide appropriate opportunities for people with disabilities to become fully integrated into the community if they chose to do so.
    The KaineLibjstanley.pst contains 669 emails sent and received by Julie A Stanley between August 2005 and January 2010.
    Subjects include: Community Integration (Implementation) Team (meeting notes, agendas, recommendations, work plans); Community Integration Advisory Commission (agendas, strategic plan, and minutes); legislation and budget (includes ARC of Virginia General Assembly Update messages and press releases); Money Follows the Person Housing Task Force Work group (agendas, meeting notes, and materials); and the Virginia Grant Consortium (agendas, meeting notes, report, and presentations).
    Correspondents include: Maureen Hollowell, Heidi Lawyer, Brandon Leonard, Teresa Preda, Jason Rachel, E. Janet Riddick, Michael Shank, Neil Sherman, and Ed Turner.
  - Series IX. Secretary of Health and Human Resources Electronic Files, Subseries F. Janet Riddick Email, 2004-2008.
    This subseries contains 338 emails in one PST file: jriddick.pst. E. Janet Riddick served as Policy Analyst for the Office of Community Integration for People with Disabilities from 2004 to her retirement in 2008. Riddick's file also contains the email of Brandon Leonard, Policy and Planning Specialist for the Office of Community Integration for People with Disabilities. Governor Mark Warner created the Office of Community Integration for People with Disabilities in 2004 by executive order (EO 61). Warner's executive order was part of the Commonwealth's response to the U.S. Supreme Court's Olmstead v. L.C. decision, the Americans with Disability Act, and the Virginians with Disabilities Act to provide appropriate opportunities for people with disabilities to become fully integrated into the community if they chose to do so.
    Jriddick.pst contains 338 emails sent and received by Janet Riddick and Brandon Leonard between September 2004 and September 2008. There are two privacy protected and confidential emails in this PST file that are restricted for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78 and 63.2-104. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: social services records.
    Subjects include: Legislation (including legislative updates on community-integration-related bills for the 2006 General Assembly session); Community Integration (Implementation) Team (meeting notes, agendas, presentations, strategic plans); and Community Integration Advisory Commission (agendas, notes, minutes).
    Correspondents include: Janet Hill, Heidi Lawyer, Brandon Leonard, Joan Manley, Richard Martin, Rob Martin, Martha Pulley, Kathie Shifflett, and Julie Stanley.
  - Series IX. Secretary of Health and Human Resources Electronic Files, Subseries G. Kristin Burhop Email, 2006-2010.
    This subseries contains 962 emails in one PST file: KaineLibkburhop.pst. Kristin Burhop served as Special/Legislative Assistant in the Office of the Secretary of Health and Human Resources from June 2006 to January 2010. Burhop was a legislative liaison and Systems Transformation Grant Project Director.
    KaineLibkburhop.pst contains 962 emails sent and received by Kristin Burhop between June 2006 and January 2010.
    Subjects include: health related regulations (pain management, midwives); legislative files related to HHR agencies/issues (legislative proposals, draft legislation, studies and annual reports to General Assembly, patron recommendations for legislation, talking points); budget development (2010-2012 biennium); agency budget reduction plans (2009); contract renewal decisions; and media alerts from HHR agencies.
    Correspondents include: Gena Boyle, Maribeth Brewster, Karin Clark, Heidi Dix, Patrick Finnerty, Carla Harris, Joe Hilbert, Raymond Hopkins, Gail Jaspen, Lynne Jeffries, Cindi Jones, Richard Martin, Marianne McGhee, Linda Nablo, Karen Remley, James Rothrock, Sandra Ryals, Margaret Schultze, Brian Shepard, Julie Stanley, Marilyn Tavenner, Wayne Turnage, Ruth Anne Walker, Mamie White, and Elaine Yeatts.
  - Series IX. Secretary of Health and Human Resources Electronic Files, Subseries H. Judith Ahern Email, 2007-2010.
    This subseries contains 6532 emails in one PST file: JAHERN.PST. Judith Ahern served as the Director of Constituent Services for the Secretary of Health and Human Resources in the Governor Tim Kaine administration from 2006 to January 2010.